<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Sunday no Sabbath A sermon preached before the Lord Bishop of Lincolne, at his Lordships visitation at Ampthill in the county of Bedford, Aug. 17. 1635. By John Pocklington Doctor of Divinitie, late fellow and president both of Pembroke Hall and Sidney Colledge in Cambridge, and chaplaine to the Right Reverend Father in God the Lord Bishop of Lincolne.</title>
            <author>Pocklington, John.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1636</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 98 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 28 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A09813</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20077</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S114780</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99850003</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99850003</idno>
            <idno type="VID">15184</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A09813)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 15184)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 933:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Sunday no Sabbath A sermon preached before the Lord Bishop of Lincolne, at his Lordships visitation at Ampthill in the county of Bedford, Aug. 17. 1635. By John Pocklington Doctor of Divinitie, late fellow and president both of Pembroke Hall and Sidney Colledge in Cambridge, and chaplaine to the Right Reverend Father in God the Lord Bishop of Lincolne.</title>
                  <author>Pocklington, John.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 50, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Young,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1636.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Cf. Folger catalogue, which gives signatures: A-G⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sunday --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sabbath --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:15184:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:15184:1"/>
            <p>SUNDAY NO SABBATH. A SERMON Preached before the Lord Biſhop of Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colne, at his Lordſhips viſitation at <hi>Ampthill</hi> in the County of <hi>Bedford, Aug.</hi> 17. 1635.</p>
            <p>BY JOHN POCKLINGTON Doctor of Divinitie, late fellow and Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent both of Pembroke Hall and Sidney Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and Chaplaine to the Right Reverend Father in God the Lord Biſhop of LINCOLNE.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>1 TIM. 6.20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>O Timothee, depoſitum cuſtodi, devitans profanas vocum no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitates, &amp; oppoſitiones falſi nominis ſcientiae, quam qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam promittentes circa fidem exciderunt.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by ROBERT YOUNG. 1636.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:15184:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:15184:2"/>
            <head>SUNDAY NO SABBATH.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>ACTS 20.7, 8.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p n="7">
                     <hi>7</hi> And upon the firſt day of the weeke, when the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples came together to breake bread, <hi>Paul</hi> preached unto them, readie to depart on the morrow, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued his ſpeech untill midnight.</p>
                  <p n="8">
                     <hi>8.</hi> And there were many lights in the upper chamber where they were gathered together.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His Text, I conceive, is not unfit for this time. In the text is <hi>ſynaxis,</hi> a meeting; and at this time there is <hi>ſynodus,</hi> a meeting.</p>
            <p>In the text is a meeting of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples; and ſuch is the meeting at this time. Hee that called the Diſciples together, and ſate Preſident in that meeting, was the
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:15184:3"/>Apoſtle <hi>Paul;</hi> and he that called us hither, and ſits Preſident in this meeting, is our Dioceſan; who can derive himſelfe the ſucceſſour of an Apoſtle: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe we ſhould have taken his call for the voice of a ſtranger, and not have here appeared. It is Saint Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtines reſolution,<note place="margin">S. Aug. cont. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nich. ep. c. <hi>4.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Succeſsio Epiſcoporum ab ipſâ ſede Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tri,</hi> is that which, amongſt other things by him named, keepes us <hi>in gremio Eccleſiae,</hi> and ſubjects us to our Biſhops juriſdiction. The meeting in the text is inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for two Actions, <hi>Breaking of bread,</hi> and <hi>Preaching.</hi> And the eſpeciall intent of this meeting is, to receive our Biſhops directions for the adminiſtration of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments and Preaching, as his Articles informe us. Hitherto, if I can but hold me by my text, I hope not to fall into impertinencies. But in the next place the day of meeting in the text jumpeth not with the day of meeting for this our Synod. For that is the firſt day of the weeke: yet this comes as neere it as may be, for with Jacob it holds his brother by the heele; this is the ſecond. And had it beene appointed on a Sunday, the authority of the Councell of Conſtantinople, Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, and Chalcedon, would have juſtified it againſt all Sabbatarians. For by the Emperours edict they were preciſely commanded to meet, and did meet, and ſate, and gave ſuffrages, and diſpatched letters on a Sun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day.</p>
            <p>But in the other circumſtances the text and the time are nothing at all allied. The place of meeting then was an upper chamber, ours a Church dedicated &amp; conſecra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for thoſe holy duties in the text, and uſed alſo for Synods. That meeting was in the night, ours in the day. They had the benefit of many lights, we of one
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:15184:3"/>great light that ruleth the day. In the text the Sermon continued till midnight; but herein if I leave not my text, you will leave me. And if none of us all follow St. Paul in preaching in an upper chamber, in the night, and till midnight, neither he, nor his ſucceſſours will taxe us. For Saint Luke is faine to make an Apologie for him in theſe reſpects, <hi>He was to depart the next mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row.</hi> So that neceſsitie put him upon that time and place; and the importunitie of his Diſciples would not be ſatisfied with a ſhorter diſcourſe. For <hi>fons abiturus,</hi> (ſaies Saint Auſtine) they knew they ſhould never ſee his face any more,<note place="margin">S. Aug. ep. <hi>86.</hi>
               </note> nor refreſh their thirſtie ſoules with thoſe waters of life that iſſued from the fountaine of his bleſſed lips; that he which could ſhake the Viper from his hand, could not finde in his heart to caſt theſe Babes from his breaſts. Therefore, contrary to his owne rules given to the Corinthians, he did adminiſter the Sacrament and preach, where men did both eat and drinke, and continued the ſame (out of order) till mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night. And ſo without any curious diviſion, I come, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my plaine manner, to handle the words in the text: and for your better memorie take them up as they lie in order, and begin with the time of this meeting.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Upon the firſt day of the weeke.]</hi> Herein I conceive foure things conſiderable. 1. what is meant by the firſt day of the weeke. 2. &amp; 3. next, when and by whom was that day appointed for holy aſſemblies to meet on. 4. when doth the holy obſervation of that day begin.</p>
            <p>For the firſt.<note place="margin">S Baſil H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xam. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>om. <hi>2.</hi> &amp; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ct. <hi>27.</hi>
               </note> The words in the Originall are one day of the <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> one being put for firſt (ſaies S. Baſil) as the evening and the morning were one day, <hi>i.e.</hi> the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:15184:4"/>firſt. So <hi>una Sabbathi</hi> is that <hi>quam primam dicimus,</hi> (ſaies St. <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) as we finde it written,<note place="margin">S. Amb. pſ. <hi>47.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 28.1. <hi>Veſperi Sabbathi quae luceſcit in primam Sabbathi,</hi> In the end of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> when the firſt day of the week began to dawne.<note place="margin">S. Aug. ep. <hi>86.</hi>
               </note> For that day (ſaies Saint Auguſtine) which three of the Evangeliſts call <hi>unam Sabbathi,</hi> one <hi>Sabbath, prima Sabbathi à Matthaeo dicitur,</hi> Saint Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thew expounds them, and calls the firſt day of the weeke. And it is manifeſt (ſaith the ſame Father) that this firſt day of the weeke is that day, <hi>qui poſteà dies Dominicus appellatus eſt,</hi> which afterward was called the Lords day.<note place="margin">S. Cyril. in Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>han. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>58.</hi>
               </note> Saint <hi>Cyril</hi> affirmes the very ſame; Chriſt appeared to his Diſciples <hi>una Sabbathi,</hi> on one <hi>Sabbath,</hi> or on the firſt day of the weeke, <hi>i.e. die Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minico,</hi> on the Lords day. It is manifeſt then, that by one day of the <hi>Sabbaths</hi> is meant the firſt day of the weeke; and the firſt day of the weeke is the Lords day. So wee ſee what is meant by the firſt day of the weeke, it is <hi>the Lords day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The next points are, when and by whom was the obſervation of the Lords day appointed. The Church (ſaith St. Ignatius) hath ſet apart one day,<note place="margin">S Ignat. ep. ad Magneſ.</note> and called it the Lords day, in confutation of thoſe ſonnes of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that deny the Lords worke performed on that day, that is, his reſurrection. So have you the time when, and the authority that did appoint the obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Lords day, delivered by Ignatius ſcholar to Saint John,<note place="margin">Niceph. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>35</hi>
               </note> that firſt ſo called it; and, as it is recorded, one of thoſe babes whom our Saviour tooke up into his armes, as his maſter was received in his boſome. The time was the time the Apoſtles lived in. The authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie was the Church.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:15184:4"/>
What meane you by the Church? Take that clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red out of St. Auguſtine,<note place="margin">S. Aug. ep. <hi>119.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Apoſtoli &amp; Apoſtolici viri ſanxerunt,</hi> the Apoſtles and Apoſtolike men have or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained, that the firſt day of the weeke ſhould be ſet a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part for the religious and ſolemne ſervice of God, becauſe our Redeemer aroſe on that day; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is called ever ſince <hi>dies Dominicus,</hi> the Lords day, <hi>&amp; ex illo caepit habere feſtivitatem,</hi> and from the very Apoſtles time and from their conſtitution, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to be kept as <hi>a feſtivall day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A feſtivall day!</hi> what meane you by that? Why <hi>à ſanctis patribus conſtitutum &amp; mandatum</hi> (ſaies the ſame Father) it is a conſtitution and command received from our holy Fathers,<note place="margin">S. Aug<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſerm. <hi>251.</hi> de temp.</note> that men ſhould leave all worldly buſineſſe on Saints daves, <hi>&amp; maximè diebus Dominicis,</hi> and eſpecially on the Lords day, that they may betake themſelves wholly to the Lords ſervice. The firſt day of the week then is the Lords day, appointed to be kept as a holy feaſt for the Lords ſervice, by the Apoſtles themſelves in their owne time. And this day which the Apoſtles call the Lords day,<note place="margin">S. Juſtin. ora<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ad Anton<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> St. Juſtine Martyr an A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolike man calls <hi>Sunday. Solis autem die communi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter omnes conventum agimus ad preces &amp; ſupplicationes,</hi> on <hi>Sunday</hi> we all meet together to prayers and ſuppli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, becauſe that is <hi>primus dies,</hi> the firſt day on which our Saviour aroſe. For he was crucified <hi>pridiè Saturni diei,</hi> the day before Saturday, and the next day after Saturday, <hi>qui ſc. Solis eſt dies,</hi> which is <hi>Sunday, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolis &amp; Diſcipulis ſuis apparuit,</hi> he appeared to his Apoſtles and Diſciples. And hereupon his Apoſtles and Diſciples thought fit to appoint and command this day to be kept holy. The Lords day then is by the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:15184:5"/>Apoſtles ſo called, and by this Apoſtolike man na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>Sunday;</hi> and may fitly ſo be called, becauſe (ſaies Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) <hi>in eo ortus Sol juſtitiae illuminat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Amb ſer. <hi>61.</hi>
               </note> the <hi>Sun of righteouſneſſe</hi> then aroſe, that enlightneth every one of us. The firſt day of the weeke then is the Lords day, and <hi>Sunday.</hi> And the Lords day was by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles themſelves in their owne time appointed for holy aſſemblies to meet on, as on a feaſt day dedicated to the Lords ſervice. And ſo hath that day beene cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, and uſed ever ſince in the true Catholike Church of God for 1554. yeares together without interrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, both in the Greeke and Latine Church.</p>
            <p>What ſhall we thinke then of Knox and Whitting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,<note place="margin">Troubles at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. pag. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> and their fellowes, that in their letter to Calvin depart from the conſtitution, ordinance, and practice of the Apoſtles and Apoſtolike men, and call not this day the Lords day, or <hi>Sunday,</hi> but with the pietie of Jero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boam make ſuch a day of it, as they have deviſed in their owne hearts, to ſerve their owne turne, and ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baptizing of it after the mind of ſome Jew hired to be the god-father thereof, call it the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and ſo diſgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with that name become both the firſt that ſo called it, and the Teſtators that have ſo bequeathed it to their Diſciples and Proſelites to be obſerved accordingly?</p>
            <p>It was full thirtie yeares before their children could turne their tongues from <hi>Sunday</hi> to hit on <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath:</hi> and if the Gileadites that met with the Ephrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites before they could frame to pronounce <hi>Shibbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth,</hi> had ſnapt theſe too, before they had got their <hi>Sabbath</hi> by the end, their counſell had brought much peace to the Church. For this name <hi>Sabbath</hi> is not a bare name, like a ſpot in their foreheads to know
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:15184:5"/>
               <hi>Labans</hi> ſheepe from <hi>Jacobs;</hi> but indeed it is a myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie of iniquitie, intended againſt the Church. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low them but their <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and you muſt allow them the ſervice that belongs to their <hi>Sabbath.</hi> Then muſt you have no Letanie, for that is no ſervice for their <hi>Sabbath,</hi> (containing ſuffrages deviſed by Pope Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory) but for <hi>Sundayes;</hi> nay,<note place="margin">Troubles at Frankf. pag. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> for Wedneſdayes and Fridayes, which muſt not ſo be uſed, for <hi>ſixe dayes thou muſt labour:</hi> nay, you muſt have no part of the Service in the Communion booke uſed, for that is Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice alſo for holy dayes,<note place="margin">Welph. detemp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> which are abominated as ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latricall, being dedicated to Saints. Well then, the <hi>Sabbath</hi> muſt be yeelded them, otherwiſe there will be no day left for God to be ſerved on.</p>
            <p>What Service then muſt you allow them for their <hi>Sabbath?</hi> Why nothing but preaching. How ſhall that be knowne? Why out of their owne mouthes. Thus ſoone after the Conventicle in London in 84. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the 31<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. yeare of the <hi>Sabbaths</hi> nativitie, writeth one of them in his letter to ſome Superintendent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, to whom he gives an account of his <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baths</hi> exerciſe: <hi>Ego ſingulis Sabbath is, ſi non alius ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniens locum ſuppleat, (cum praeſcriptà Leiturgeias formulâ nihil habens commercit) in caetu concionem ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beo, idque reverendorum fratrum conſilio;</hi> I preach e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very <hi>Sabbath</hi> in the congregation, (having nothing at all to doe with the order preſcribed in the booke of Common Prayer;) and this he does, not of his owne head, but by the counſell of the reverend brethren, delivered doubtleſſe in that late Synode.</p>
            <p>Now you ſee the Common Prayer booke, which the Kings Majeſties authority in cauſes Eccleſiaſticall,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:15184:6"/>with the Convocation houſe, have appointed, and the Parliament the reunto aſſented, is clean caſt out of their <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and no ſervice allowed or uſed but preaching. Marvaile not then at the caſting out of lawfull ſports; their zeale could and did diſpence with them well e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for a long time together, as they of Genevah and the Low-countries (even ſitting the Synode of Dort) did, and ſtill doe. But the plot with us will not beare them, for they muſt gaine elbow roome for their <hi>Sabbaths</hi> exerciſe, or preaching, falſely ſo called, being for the moſt part (as their hearers will juſtifie) but violent diſcourſes, and perſonall invectives againſt the preſent State, and ſettled lawes of the Land, with the Governours, thereby to get themſelves magnified for the great power of God with Simon, that having cryed downe all Lawes, Eccleſiaſticall and Temporall too in time that ſute not with their <hi>Sabbath</hi> doctrine, they may be able (making their reliance on their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veigled thouſands whereof they bragge) to put their hands to their mouthes,<note place="margin">Mar. ju. epiles.</note> and to ſay with him in the ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry,<note place="margin">Petition to his Majeſtie in <hi>1603.</hi> Richard. <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Behold the fountaine from whence all lawes for go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernement of Church and Common wealth muſt ſhortly ſpring.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You ſee then what the plot was that bred, and ſtill keepes the name of <hi>Sabbath</hi> on foot; that if St. John or the Apoſtles that firſt called and appointed the Lords day, ſhould come amongſt them, and happen to call it the Lords day, they would quickly finde him to be none of their Tribe, nor for their turne, being <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, without his watch word of the <hi>Sabbath.</hi> But if Juſtin that bleſſed Martyr ſhould be ſo profane as to call it <hi>Sunday,</hi> he would be in danger under their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:15184:6"/>diſcipline to be martyred the ſecond time for not ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring their idoll <hi>Sabbath,</hi> as he was under Antonius for not worſhipping Jupiter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> Secondly, if the Lords day was appointed and kept by the Apoſtles, what ſhall we ſay to thoſe turbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent ſpirits (as maſter Calvin calls them) <hi>qui tumultu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>antur ob diem Dominicum,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Calv. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> c. <hi>8</hi> S. <hi>33.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> that are all up in a hurly-bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for being abridged of their Chriſtian libertie, and made to obſerve dayes and Feaſts, and particularly the Lords day? Whereupon it was ſadly demurr'd upon, even in Genevah,<note place="margin">Barcl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> paroen. l. <hi>1</hi> c. <hi>13.</hi>
               </note> to have that day altered to Thurſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day; and himſelfe holds it alterable. What ſhall wee thinke alſo of the Centuriſts,<note place="margin">Cent. <hi>1.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi> c.<hi>6.</hi> de fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> that not onely ſay there is no place of Scripture to command the obſervation of the Lords day;<note place="margin">Cent. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>6.</hi> pag. <hi>11</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> but that the contentions raiſed by Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cetus and Victor, Popes of Rome, touching the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of Eaſter on the Lords day, doe ſufficiently de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, that for two hundred yeares after Chriſt ſome kept the <hi>Sabbath</hi> holy, ſome the Lords day; and that they were falſe Apoſtles that attempted at firſt to bind the Church to the obſervation of Feaſts, as of the Lords day: and for this cauſe they ſticke the myſterie of iniquitie on the foreheads of thoſe two bleſſed Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> To that part of the objection which is framed out of the Centuriſts, ſome perhaps would anſwer, that the guiſe of the Centuriſts is to uſe the Catholike Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers and holy Martyrs as Balaam uſed his Aſſe. For if they wil not go that way that they would have them, though Gods Angel ſuffer them not ſo to doe, but the Spirit of truth lead them quite otherwiſe, they fall up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, and uſe them as rudely as he did the Aſſe. A
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:15184:7"/>wrong which cannot but bee highly diſpleaſing to that good God, who was ſo moved upon the ſight of the injury done the poore beaſt, that hee was upon the point to have taken a ſharpe revenge upon the falſe hypocrite, in habit of a Prophet, for the ſame.</p>
            <p>But with cruell Balaam I will not compare them, becauſe he wiſht for a ſword to be avenged of the poore Aſſe; whereas theſe, like diligent Schoolemaſters, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine the exerciſes of the ancient Fathers, ſhew them their errours, tell them of the many ſpots and blots they finde in them, and let them ſee how they are put to the trouble to correct them at every turne; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon their patience is ſo moved, that they rebuke them ſometime with very ſharpe language: and when all is done, they are ſo aſhamed of divers things they heare from them, that they ſet them to ſchoole againe to learne their leſſons backward.</p>
            <p>This their diligence and paines in correcting and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping the Fathers, as one wipes a diſh that turneth it up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide downe, is not well accepted on all hands: for ſome paſſionate men thinke they whip the Fathers without cauſe, and for not running the way of their errours, which theſe Auditors account to be ſo many, and ſo coſtly too, that the Merchant payes more for them than for all the truths,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> morall, naturall, ſupernaturall, that are in Ariſtotle, Plato, or the bleſſed Bible, though you give the Apocrypha leave to be bound up with it. I would be loath to ſay as Saint Paul doth of the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of Epimenides, <hi>This witneſſe is true.</hi> But be it truth, or ſome counterfeit, like Jeroboams wife, their credit is eclipſed, and their teſtimonie abated by their doings. So I leave them till anon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:15184:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Secondly, I anſwer, true it is, that Saint Paul and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Apoſtles preached to the Jewes in the Synagogue on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day, becauſe they would meet upon no other: but it is untrue, that they ſet that day apart to preach unto the Gentiles, or the Jews either. They were falſe Apoſtles that laboured to lay that yoak on the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples neckes, whom Saint Paul oppoſed with all his might, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.16. <hi>Gal.</hi> 4.10. and did utterly reject their <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and appointed no day of publick meetings but the firſt day of the weeke, when their collections were ever made, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 16.1. and ſo continued to be made on that day, and on no day elſe, in all ſucceeding ages. And becauſe Saint Paul did keepe the firſt day of the weeke, and oppoſed the obſervation of the Jewiſh <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> therefore the Ebionites (ſay St. Irenaeus and Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius) rejected his writings, <hi>Apoſtatam legis dicentes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Irer. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>26.</hi> S. Ep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. <hi>31.</hi>
               </note> rating him for an Apoſtata.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe the bleſſed Martyrs in the Primitive Church,<note place="margin">Euſeb. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>24.</hi> S. Ignatap. <hi>3.</hi> ad M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>g.</note> by the doctrine and example of Saint Paul and the Apoſtles, ſo unfeignedly abhorred the obſervation of the Jewiſh <hi>Sabbath,</hi> that they eſteemed the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers thereof, and the contemners of the Lords day, the very ſonnes of perdition, enemies of our Saviour, and ſellers of Chriſt: and, as Saint Juſtin Martyrtells Trypho,<note place="margin">S. Juſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Triph. Tom. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> they gladly endured the moſt horrible tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments that men and divels could deviſe to inflict upon them, rather than yeeld <hi>Sabbatha veſtra &amp; ſolennes dies obſervare,</hi> to keepe your <hi>Sabbaths</hi> and dayes of ſolemne aſſemblies; which (ſaith he) could not hurt us, were they not forbidden us by the doctrine and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice of the Apoſtles, and Chriſt himſelfe.<note place="margin">S. Juſt. ad An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton.</note> But the obſervation of <hi>Sunday</hi> was ſo generally and religiouſly
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15184:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>obſerved of all Chriſtians, that then was the common meeting of all, <hi>qui vel in oppidis vel rure degunt,</hi> both Citizens and Country men. All ſorts of Chriſtians met on <hi>Sundayes,</hi> and none on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day but Jewes onely.</p>
            <p>With what face then dare the Centuriſts vent ſuch untruths, that the keeping of the Lords day was a thing indifferent for two hundred yeeres? And with what conſcience dare they forge thoſe to be falſe Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, that were the bringers in of the obſervation of Feaſts, and particularly of the Lords day? Or with what conſcience dare they uſe the Martyrs of God, members of Chriſts body, ſo unworthily, as to make the bleſſed Saints in heaven, fellow heires with Chriſt Jeſus, meet veſſels for the myſterie of iniquitie to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin to worke in, who did no more than either was ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Apoſtles and Apoſtolike men before themſelves, or was afterward confirmed by the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Nice, the Edicts of Conſtantine and his ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſours, the Decrees of the Councell of Conſtantinople, and other Synods, as well in the Greeke as Latine Church, in all ſucceeding ages?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But they ſay there is no place of Scripture to command the obſervation of the Lords day, but onely the Tradition from the Apoſtles; therefore the day may be altered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> Be it ſo: yet (as Chemnitius excellently ſaies) though we be not bound by any neceſſity of law <hi>in Novo Teſtamento,</hi>
               <note place="margin">C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em. Exam. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt. <hi>4.</hi> pars.</note> in the New Teſtament to obſerve the Lords day for ſolemne aſſemblies, <hi>barbarica tamen petulantia,</hi> yet were it barbarous ſaucineſſe to refuſe to obſerve the cuſtome of the Apoſtles and Primitive
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:15184:8"/>Church. For (as Saint Auguſtine ſaies) wherein the Scripture hath determined nothing, <hi>mos populi Dei,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Aug. ep. Caſ. <hi>86.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; inſtituta majorum pro lege tenenda ſunt,</hi> the cuſtome of Gods people, and the ordinance of our Elders, are to be obſerved as lawes. And in this caſe for any man to doubt whether he ſhould relinquiſh and abandon his owne new devices, <hi>&amp; ita faciendum,</hi> and that it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes him to doe as he ſees the whole Church of God to doe, <hi>inſolentiſsimae inſaniae eſt,</hi> is an inſolencie with madneſſe to boot (ſaies Saint Auguſtine.<note place="margin">S. Aug aep. <hi>119.</hi> Ja.</note>) And to talke with ſuch, <hi>interminata orietur luctatio,</hi> were to uphold wrangling world without end.</p>
            <p n="3">3 If the firſt day of the weeke be the Lords day, we muſt looke to doe the Lords worke on it, and not trench upon him by doing our owne worke thereon. For no excuſe of buſineſſe ought to keepe us from the ſervice of God on that day. No neceſſitie is a greater tyrant than poverty, yet is that no good excuſe for thy abſence from Church (ſaies Saint Chryſoſtome) to ſay thou art poore, and muſt follow thy buſineſſe.<note place="margin">S. Chryſoft. hom. <hi>24.</hi> de bap. Chriſti.</note> For God hath not taken to himſelfe the greateſt part of the dayes of the weeke, but hath given thee ſixe, <hi>unam vero ſibi reliquit,</hi> and left himſelfe but one; yet wilt thou finde out the thiefe povertie to ſteale that away from him too, as ſacrilegious perſons doe conſecrate things. But what doe I ſpeake <hi>de integro die,</hi> of a whole day? Doe but that in keeping the Lords day which the widow did in her almes, that gave two mites, <hi>ſic tu duas horas,</hi> ſo give the Lord two houres. This if you doe not, beware you loſe not <hi>integrorum annorum labores,</hi> the labours of many whole yeares.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Qu.</hi> May then no worke of our owne be done on
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:15184:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:15184:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:15184:10"/>the Lords day, not ſo much as out of the times of the Lords ſervice?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> Out of doubt there may; yea, though we ſhould ſuppoſe that Chriſtians are bound to keepe the Lords day as ſtrictly as our Saviour kept the <hi>Sabbath.</hi> For our Saviour (ſaies Epiphanius) <hi>non artem fabri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, lignariam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Epip<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>2.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>2.</hi> ber. <hi>66.</hi> p. <hi>229.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>aut ferrariam,</hi> did not follow the trade of a Carpenter or Smith on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day, though he was ſo poore that he uſed Joſephs trade, and made both Carts and Ploughs, yet <hi>converſatione &amp; doctrinâ,</hi> by his doctrine and courſe of life he ſhewed that ſome workes of our owne might be done on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> out of the times of divine ſervice; for himſelfe made clay, <hi>eſt autem opu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> lutum ſubigere,</hi> and to make clay is a kinde of worke: a worke neither of neceſſity nor charity; for had it ſo pleaſed him, the worke of charity had taken place before the clay could have been tempered. He commanded alſo the Cripple, <hi>grabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum tollere,</hi> to carry away his bed, which then needed not, for the arranteſt Phariſee theefe in Jeruſalem would not have medled with it on that day. The Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples alſo by his doctrine and example (ſaies the ſame Father) <hi>ſpicas vellunt, torrent, &amp; edunt,</hi> do plucke and parch their corne on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day. And there was no law (ſaies Saint Irenaeus) that forbade them ſo to doe:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>metere autem &amp; colligere in horreum lex vetabat,</hi> but the law forbade reaping and carrying into the barne on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day. His reaſon is this, <hi>continere enim ſe jubeb at lex ab omni opere ſervili, (i.e.) ab omni avaritiâ quae per negotiationem &amp; reliquo terreno actu <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gitatur,</hi> The law forbiddeth all ſervile workes, wherein covetouſneſſe ſticketh as a naile betweene two
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:15184:10"/>ſtones. Some ſmall chares then of our owne may be done on the Lords day, out of the times of the Lords ſervice.</p>
            <p>Secondly, meate may be dreſt, and Feaſts may be kept on the Lords day by Chriſts example,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Luc.</hi> 14.13.</note> who was at a feaſt on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day; and none ought to blame us for doing the like. For <hi>rectè Eccleſiae feſta colunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Aug. de temp. ſer. <hi>253.</hi> &amp; <hi>255.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>qui Eccleſiae filios ſe eſſe recognoſcunt,</hi> they doe well to keepe the Feaſts of the Church, that remember them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to be the ſonnes of the Church. This doctrine Saint Auguſtine taught his people, <hi>Novit ſanctitas ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra fraires,</hi> my brethren, your holineſſe knoweth very well that to day <hi>conſecrationem altaris celebramus,</hi> we celebrate the Feaſt for the conſecration of the Altar, <hi>in quo unctus vel benedictus eſt lapis, in quo divina ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficia conſecrantur, ac meritò gaudentes celebramus;</hi> and wee doe well to keepe this feaſt with joy, not with wanton, lewd, or unchaſte joy. (Saint Auſtine is no Proctor to plead for Baal, nor any that follow him.) For, <hi>neſcio qua fronte</hi> (ſaith he) I cannot tell with what conſcience he can ſhew a cheerefull countenance <hi>in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taris conſecratione,</hi> that is not preciſe <hi>in cordis ſui altari munditiam cuſtodire,</hi> to preſerve purity in the altar of his heart.</p>
            <p>The Lords day then is and ought to bee kept as a Feaſt, as the <hi>Sabbath</hi> was.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Judith.</hi> 10.2.</note> For <hi>magnum ſcandalum</hi> (ſaies Saint Auguſtine) nay <hi>magnum nefas</hi> (ſaies Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian) it is a great ſcandall,<note place="margin">S. Aug. ep. <hi>86.</hi> Tert. de Coro. Mil.</note> and a foule ſinne to faſt on the Lords day. Therefore we condemne the Mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chees (ſaies Saint Ambroſe) that faſt on <hi>Sundayes.</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Amb. ep. <hi>33.</hi> l. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> We are bound to faſt on Fridayes, and of feaſt on <hi>Sundayes;</hi> ſo have we a day <hi>&amp; amaritudinis &amp; laetitiae; in illo
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:15184:11"/>jejunemus, illo reficiamur;</hi> to faſt on the one, to feaſt on the other. The Jewes themſelves (ſaies Tertullian) kept not their <hi>Sabbath</hi> with faſting: for <hi>pridianâ pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raturâ,</hi> by their proviſion of two Omers for a man, it plainely appeareth that they made as large a meale on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> as on any day elſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob.</hi> But they were commanded to dreſſe their <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath</hi> dinner the day before, and the Commandement ſaies, <hi>On it thou ſhalt doe no maner of worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> Not to diſpute it further,<note place="margin">S. Aug. ep. <hi>119.</hi> c. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> how, or to what the Jewes were bound upon their <hi>Sabbath,</hi> however, this nothing concernes us Chriſtians, if we underſtand the Commandement aright: for though all the nine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements <hi>ſic obſervantur ut ſonant,</hi> are to be kept according to the letter; <hi>obſervare tamen diem Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thi, non ad literam jubemur ſecundum etium ab opere corporali, ſicut obſervant Judaei,</hi> yet we Chriſtians are not commanded to obſerve the <hi>Sabbath</hi> after the letter by a ſtrict reſt, as did the Jewes; nor the Lords day af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the maner of the Jewiſh <hi>Sabbath:</hi> for of all the ten Commandements, the third, which concerneth the <hi>Sabbath, figurativè intelligendum eſt,</hi> is to be under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood figuratively. For this Commandement was gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven for no other end but onely for a ſigne (ſaies Saint Irenaeus) out of the Prophet Ezechiel,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Iren. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. c. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> cap. 20. and out of the Law of Moſes, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31. and then ſhewes whereof it was a ſigne. <hi>Sabbath a perſeverantiam totius diei erga Deum deſervitionis edocebant,</hi> their <hi>Sabbath</hi> taught our continuall ſervice of God;<note place="margin">Orig. ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>28.</hi>
               </note> which <hi>Origen</hi> calls <hi>Sabbathum Chriſtianum,</hi> a Chriſtian <hi>Sabbath.</hi> And becauſe no man is juſtified either by the <hi>Sabbath</hi> or Circumciſion, therefore <hi>in ſigno data ſunt populo,</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:15184:11"/>they were given the people for a ſigne. This Theodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret largely ſheweth out of the plaine words of the Prophet Ezechiel, cap. 20. ver. 11.<note place="margin">S. Theod. in E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zech.</note> The <hi>Sabbath</hi> was none of thoſe Commandements that could give life to the obſervers, but was given them onely to be a ſigne, <hi>in ſignum temporis illius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tert. de pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> lib. c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> (as Tertullian ſpeakes) and not <hi>in ſallutis praerogativam,</hi> not to bring them ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, but to make them knowne from other Nations. Other Nations that deſcended of Abraham uſed cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion as well as the Jewes, but no Nation kept the <hi>Sabbath</hi> but Jewes onely. Therefore 1541. years they were knowne by that ſigne to be Gods people: but the keeping of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> made neither them nor the Phariſees to be Gods people. This is evident. For A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham (ſaith Saint Irenaeus) was juſtified and called the friend of God,<note place="margin">S. Iren. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>30.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>ſine obſervatione Sabbathorum,</hi> without keeping any <hi>Sabbaths.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Nay, there was not any of the Patriarchs (ſaith Tertullian) that kept the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> neither Adam,<note place="margin">Tert. adv. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daeos de praeſer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> c. <hi>2.4.</hi>
               </note> Enoch, Noah, Abraham, nor Melchizedek, for 2455. years, yet were they juſt men, and obtained ſalvation. This is ſo cleare a truth, that the Jewes could not denie it: and Trypho doth confeſſe it, being preſſed thereunto by Saint Juſtin. And for this 1635.<note place="margin">S. Juſt. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Tryph. Tom. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> yeares it hath not beene kept in the Chriſtian world. <hi>Manifeſtum eſt igitur</hi> (ſaies Tertullian) it is manifeſt therefore, that that cannot be morall, nor perpetuall, that began but with Moſes,<note place="margin">S. Tuſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. l. <hi>2.</hi> in Tryph</note> (as Saint Juſtin Martyr ſayes) and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with Chriſt, when hee nailed all the ceremoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all law to his Croſſe, with thoſe words, <hi>Conſumma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt,</hi> it is finiſhed. Therefore the third Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement, (as Saint Auſtine) or the fourth (as
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:15184:12"/>Joſephus and other Fathers call it) touching the <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> muſt be underſtood onely figuratively, and not after the letter, as the other nine commandements are. This is the doctrine of antiquitie, which hath gotten a <hi>placet</hi> from Gomarus,<note place="margin">Goma. inveſt. ſab. c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> whoſe followers may perhaps embrace the ſame.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ob. Dicunt autem Judaei, quòd primordio, &amp;c.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tertul. de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrip. c. <hi>2.</hi> &amp; <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> But a Jew will object and ſay (ſaies Tertullian) that God from the beginning did ſanctifie the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the <hi>Sabbath</hi> ought to be kept holy, and no maner of worke muſt be done thereon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sol.</hi> This is the very argument which Marcion lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of the Phariſees,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>John.</hi> 9.16.</note> and blaſphemouſly uſeth to prove Chriſt not to the Sonne of God, becauſe he carried himſelfe ſo croſſe to his Fathers actions and Lawes. For the <hi>Sabbath</hi> which his Father ſanctified and reſted on, <hi>operatione deſtruxit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Tert. in Mar. l. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> he profaned and overthrew by working on it: ſo did his Diſciples, for <hi>cibum operati</hi> (marke how pure this blaſphemous Hereticke was) they dreſſe their meate on the <hi>Sabbath.</hi> My anſwer therefore is this, that the Law-giver beſt knew how to obſerve his owne lawes; and if his Fathers reſt did not binde him from doing ſome worke, no more doth it us. Beſides, we ſee the Patriaches, even Melchizedek himſelfe, a Prieſt of the moſt high God, did not take themſelves bound to reſt on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> at all. For though they ſaw Gods example, yet they heard no commandement to enjoyne them to reſt on that day as he did; therefore they never obſerved the <hi>Sabbath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, though a Jew will little regard what the Patriarches did, or what all good Chriſtians reſolve
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:15184:12"/>and practice, but will force the Law-giver to keepe his owne law, not after his owne meaning but after theirs, as the Phariſees did our Saviour, ſaying, This man is not of God, becauſe he keepeth not the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day, <hi>viz.</hi> as they conſtrued and expounded the Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement for the obſervation thereof: yet that nothing concernes us that keepe the Lords day by vertue of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolical conſtitution and tradition of holy Church, and not the <hi>Sabbath</hi> by force of the fourth Comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement, which the Apoſtles by Chriſts doctrine and example underſtood <hi>ſolutum,</hi> to be diſſolved. And, <hi>cujus vis ſoluta nec nomen haerebat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Amb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th Lu. <hi>6.</hi> l. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> (ſaies Saint Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe) when the <hi>Sabbath</hi> loſt his force it forfeited the name; therefore ought not ſo to be called: and ſo having loſt both force and name, is become nothing at all but a meere Idoll. An Idoll hath the ſhape of ſomething, but becauſe it hath eyes and ſees not, &amp;c. it is nothing in the world. So though their <hi>Sabbath</hi> hath the name of one of the Jewes holy dayes, yet keepeth it not neither the day they kept, nor the ſervice belonging to it, and ſo is become nothing in the world.</p>
            <p>True it is, that ſome that with great zeale and little judgement exclaime againſt recreations, and dreſſing of meat, and the like, on <hi>Sundayes,</hi> muſt make a <hi>Sabbath</hi> of <hi>Sunday,</hi> and keepe up that name, otherwiſe their many citations of Scripture, mentioning onely the <hi>Sabbath</hi> of being applied to <hi>Sunday,</hi> will appeare ſo ridiculouſly diſtorted and wry-neckt, that they will be a ſcorne and deriſion to the ſimpleſt of their now deluded Auditors, who are abuſed with the name of a Chriſtian <hi>Sabbath</hi> out of <hi>Origen,</hi> which is not kept on <hi>Sunday</hi> onely,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> but every day. Chriſt is our Chriſtian <hi>Sabbath</hi> (ſaith
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:15184:13"/>Origen) and he that lives in Chriſt, <hi>ſemper in Sabbatho vivit, requieſcendo ab operibus malis, operatur autem opera juſtitiae inceſſanter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others alſo for the plot-ſake muſt uphold the name of <hi>Sabbath,</hi> that ſtalking behind it they may ſhoot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Service appointed for the Lords day. Hence it is that ſome for want of wit, ſome for too much, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore the <hi>Sabbath</hi> as an Image dropt downe from Jupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and cry before it, as they did before the golden Calfe, <hi>This is an holy day unto the Lord;</hi> whereas indeed it is the great Diana of the Epheſians as they uſe it, whereby the mindes of their Proſelytes are ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed and bewitched, that they cannot reſolve whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſinne be greater to bowle, ſhoot, or daunce on their <hi>Sabbath,</hi> than to commit murder, or the father to cut the throate of his owne childe. All which doubts would ſoon be reſolved by plucking the vizzard of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> from the face of the Lords day, which doth as well and truely become it as the Crowne of thornes did the Lord himſelfe. This was platted to expoſe him to damnable deriſion, and that was plotted to impoſe on it deteſtable ſuperſtition.</p>
            <p>Yet to die for it they will call it a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming in their zealous ignorance or guilefull zeale, to be thought to ſpeake the Scripture phraſe, when indeed the dregs of Aſhdod flow from their mouthes. For that day which they nickname the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> is either no day at all, or not the day that they meane. It were well therefore that they would forbeare to ſpeake ſtrange languages in the Church for Saint Pauls ſake, and uſe them then when they all meet together in new England amongſt them that underſtand the language;
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:15184:13"/>for with us the <hi>Sabbath</hi> is Saturday, and no day elſe. No ancient Father, Father! Nay, no learned man, Heathen or Chriſtian, tooke it otherwiſe from the beginning of the world till the beginning of their ſchiſme in 1554. And if wee finde the word other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe uſed in ſome writings that of late come unto our hands, blame not the Clerkes, good men, for it, nor intitle the miſpriſion any higher, or otherwiſe than to theſe pretenders to pietie, who for their owne ends have for a long time deceived the world with their zealous and moſt ignorant or cunning cla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, and rung the name of <hi>Sabbath</hi> ſo commonly into all mens eares, that not Clerkes onely, but men of judgement, learning and vertue, not heeding per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure ſo much as is requiſite, what crafty and wicked device may be menaged under the vaile of a faire word uſed in Gods law, doe likewiſe ſuffer the ſame often to ſcape the doore of their lips, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt the drift of the deviſers in the cloſet of their hearts.</p>
            <p>I will now ſhut up this point in Saint Hilaries words.<note place="margin">S. Hilar. l. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Non ſum neſcius difficillimo me aſperrimo<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tempore haec diſſerere, multis jam per omnes fermè Romani Imperii provincias Eccleſiis morbo peſtiferae hujus praedicationis infectis, &amp; velut ad piae fidei hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jus malà uſurpatam perſuaſionem, longo doctrinae uſu, &amp; ementito nomine verae religionis imbutis, non igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans difficilem eſſe ad emendationis profectum, volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem: quam in erroris ſui ſtudio per plurimorum aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſum authoritas publicae ſententiae contineret. Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vis enim eſt, &amp; periculoſus error inplurimis, &amp; mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum lapſus, etiamſi ſe intellig at, tamen exurgendi pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dore
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:15184:14"/>authoritatem ſibi praeſumit, ex numero habens hoc impudentiae, ut quod errat, intelligentiam eſſe ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritatis aſſerat, dum minus erroris eſſe exiſtimatur in multis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There are ſo many that ſee ſo little benefit will be ſuckt out of the conſtitutions of the Apoſtles, pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice and tradition of holy Church, doctrine of god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and learned Fathers, that they have got them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves heapes of teachers, that to ſerve their owne turnes will call and keep the Lords day as a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and ſo proclaime it with ſuch lowd outcries, that the voice of truth will become ſilence, and her ſelfe made errour, and ſo made to beleeve of her ſelfe, or to forgoe her owne modeſty, and to beleeve none but her ſelfe.</p>
            <p>But with Moſes, <hi>liberavi animam meam,</hi> being called hither very unwillingly, I have ſet before you good and evill, light and darkneſſe, life and death, the doctrine and practice of the Church of God, and the leaven of Phariſees, and faſhion of Schiſma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tickes and Novelliſts; chuſe which you will, and the Lord be your guide. Onely of this be you well aſſured, that if you will have Manna rained downe unto you, you muſt forgoe your <hi>Sabbath,</hi> and ſticke onely to the Lords day: for <hi>in noſtrâ Dominicâ die ſemper Dominus pluit Manna,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Orig. ſuper <hi>15.</hi> Exod. hom. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; in Sabbatho non pluit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The laſt point touching the day of meeting is, When doth the Lords day begin?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Reſp.</hi> I anſwer,<note place="margin">S. Ambra. in Pſ. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>7.</hi>
               </note> out of Saint Ambroſe, The firſt day of the weeke began when the <hi>Sabbath</hi> ended. The <hi>Sabbath</hi> ended when Chriſt aroſe. Chriſt the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:15184:14"/>true light aroſe with the light and ſpring of the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; for <hi>veſperi Sabbathi quae luceſcit in primam Sabbathi,</hi> are Saint Matthews words. <hi>Nihil pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chrius, nihil expreſsius</hi> (ſaith hee) this place is as fit and pat for our purpoſe as may be. The <hi>Sabbaths</hi> evening is in the light of the firſt day of the weeke.</p>
            <p>So Saint Leo reſolveth Dioſcorus Patriarch of Alexandria, <hi>veſpera Sabbathi initium diei Dominici,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Leo epiſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d Dioſc.</note> the beginning of the Lords day is in the end of the <hi>Sabbath.</hi> The end of the <hi>Sabbath</hi> is in the light of the firſt day of the weeke. Looke then for Jacobs hand on Eſau's heele, or the beginning of the Lords day in the end of the <hi>Sabbath.</hi> But Saint Nyſſen is more punctuall and cleere:<note place="margin">S. Nyſſen. dere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſur. orat. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> the Lords day (ſaith he) begins at Cock-crowing, <hi>atque in hoc ipſo articulo temporis,</hi> and at that very knot and joint of time: For then end we our <hi>Sabbaths,</hi> or Saturdaies faſt, and then begin we <hi>nos oblectare &amp; laetari,</hi> to keepe our <hi>Sundayes</hi> feaſt, and that by an ancient cuſtome, which all are bound to obſerve. For <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſaith he) doth not ſignifie the evening, or that part of the night which is <hi>poſt occaſum Solis,</hi> after Sun ſet; but the riſe of the morning, with which the <hi>Sabbath</hi> ended.</p>
            <p>Yet for all this the Church by way of preparation for the better ſanctification of the Lords day, hath prudently and piouſly appointed holy offices to be uſed on the Eve before. And in obedience to this po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive conſtitution of holy Church Saint Auguſtine would have his hearers to obſerve the Lords day,<note place="margin">S. Aug. ſer. de tem. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>à veſperâ ad veſperam,</hi> from Even to Even, <hi>ſicut anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis praeceptum eſt de Sabbatho,</hi> as it was alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:15184:15"/>the Jewes concerning the <hi>Sabbath.</hi> And therefore (ſaith he) look that from Saturday at Even, <hi>uſ que ad veſperam diei Dominici,</hi> till the Lords day at even, we ſet aſide all rurall and worldly buſineſſe, <hi>ut ſolo divino culiui vacemus,</hi> that we may attend onely on the Lords ſervice, and begin to repaire to the Church to evening prayer on Saturday nights; and he that cannot ſo doe, let him be ſure to pray at home.</p>
            <p>Remember then that you which will needs have the Lords day a <hi>Sabbath,</hi> doe ſet aſide all buſineſſe, and flocke to the Church to ſay or heare Service on Saturday Evens; which hitherto you have not done, notwithſtanding the order of the Church, which preſcribeth that part of that day to prepare us for the more devout obſervation of the Lords day. Thus much of the day of meeting, <hi>The firſt day of the weeke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 In the next place, we have in the next words to conſider of the perſons that then met. Theſe were not Jewes, for then the <hi>Sabbath</hi> had beene the day of their meeting; but Gentiles, Aſians, Macedonians, Theſſalonians, Paul, with his companions and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples. Now Paul had ordered before this time in Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latia, and in Corinth, that his Diſciples were to have their meetings on the firſt day of the weeke, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto they ſubmitted themſelves. For on the firſt day of the week they now met, and ſo did the whole Church of God by their example for ever after. Wherefore their obedience and humility would bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter beſeeme us, than the pride and oppoſition of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>otrephes againſt St. John, and St Paul, and the whole
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:15184:15"/>Church of God, about the day of meeting, or the Service thereon uſed, onely for preheminence ſake.</p>
            <p n="3">3 Now I come in the next place to the holy duties wherin the Apoſtle and his Diſciples ſpent the Lords day. The firſt of theſe is breaking of bread. How is that done? St. Auguſtine tells us, <hi>ſicut frangitur in Sacramento corporis Chriſti,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Aug. ep. <hi>86.</hi>
               </note> not as bread is broken in a Taverne, but as it is broken in the Sacrament of the Lords body. Therefore the Syriac plainely calleth this breaking of bread, receiving the Euchariſt. So doth Juſtin Martyr. And none is ſo fit as he to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound St. Auſtins <hi>ſicut,</hi> to tell us how bread was bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the holy Euchariſt in thoſe primitive times. This he doth in his information given thereof unto Antoninus plus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sunday</hi> (ſaies he) is the day of our meeting,<note place="margin">S. Juſtin. orat, ad Anton.</note> for taking that nouriſhment which with us is called the Euchariſt. Then the brethren come together <hi>ad communes preces &amp; ſupplicationes,</hi> to common pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers and ſupplications: then are read the writings of the Prophets and Apoſtles: <hi>deinde Lectore quieſcente,</hi> when the Reader hath finiſhed all divine Service, <hi>Praeſidens orationem habet,</hi> he that hath the chiefe place maketh an Oration or Sermon, and inſtructs the people, and exhorts them to imitate thoſe excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent things which they have heard read.</p>
            <p>Here is reading of prayers and leſſons, both out of the Old and New Teſtament, and after them a Sermon; and the Sermon doth not juſtle out any part of divine Service, though the Preſident or Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop himſelfe made it. Thus the firſt Service en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth with a Sermon.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:15184:16"/>
And now begins the ſecond Service. <hi>Sub haec con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurgimus omnes, &amp;c.</hi> prayers being finiſhed, and the Sermon done, we all ſtand up at once and poure out our prayers. Stand up and pray! Marvaile not at this. For in the Primitive Church prayers on the Lords day were performed ſtanding, in memory of Chriſts reſurrection. And it was not lawfull <hi>de ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niculis adorare,</hi> to pray kneeling, as appeares out of Tertullian,<note place="margin">Tertul. de Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. mil. Concil. Nic. Can. <hi>30.</hi> S. Bafil. de Sp. Sancto. c. <hi>27.</hi> S. Aug. ep. <hi>119.</hi> S. Epiph. l. <hi>3.</hi> To. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> and the Nicene Councell, and the Fathers that ſucceeded.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>precibus finitis,</hi> prayers being ended, <hi>ei qui fratribus praeeſt, offertur panis, &amp;c.</hi> Bread, wine, and water are offered to the Prieſt, who taketh the ſame, and with all his might courageouſly <hi>preces &amp; grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arum actiones profundit,</hi> poures out prayers and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedictions over them: and then all the people give a cheerefull acclamation, and cry <hi>Amen.</hi> Then is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtribution made <hi>cuique praeſenti,</hi> to every one pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; doubtleſſe to lay men as well as to Prieſts and Deacons. Then alſo the richer ſort contribute what they thinke fit, which is laid up for the uſe of the poore.</p>
            <p>Here are reading of prayers and leſſons, expoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of Scripture, ſupplications, benedictions, ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations to the Prieſt, collections for the poore, diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution of the Sacrament, all required to breaking of bread, <hi>ficut frangitur in Sacramento corporis Chriſti,</hi> as it is broken in the Euchariſt. And ſo we ſee how the uſe of our firſt and ſecond Service is founded on, and agreeth with the practice of the Primitive Church, by the teſtimonie of this holy Martyr. Yet this may more clearely be delineated out of the
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:15184:16"/>Fathers that ſucceeded him. Chriſtian Churches in the Primitive times had theſe diſtinct places in them: there was <hi>Sacrarium, Presbyterium,</hi> and <hi>Auditori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um:</hi> the <hi>Sacrarium</hi> or holy place, was diſtinguiſhed from the Presbyterie by certaine liſts and railes: the Presbyterie alſo was divided from the Auditorie, Nave, and body of the Church <hi>per cancellos,</hi> by a certaine partition that gave it the name of a Chaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell. In the holy place ſtood the Altar, or Lords boord, and not in the body of the Church. In the Presbyterie was placed <hi>Cathedra Epiſcopi, &amp; exedrae Presbyterorum,</hi> the Biſhops Chaire or Throne, and ſtalls for Prieſts. For anciently none elſe, not ſo much as Deacons, were permitted to ſit in the Church. In the Auditorie ſtood the Pulpit, or Readers Tribunall (as Saint Cyprian calls it.) Now the Service that was performed <hi>in Sacrario,</hi> was much different from that which was done <hi>in Auditorio.</hi> None were allowed to come and ſtand within the liſts of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly place, where the Altar was fixed, but the Prieſts,<note place="margin">Concil. Arel. Can. <hi>15.</hi> S. Cyp. l. <hi>1.</hi> ep. <hi>9.</hi>
               </note> whoſe office it was, <hi>non niſi altari deſervire,</hi> to ſtand and ſerve at the altar, and none but they.<note place="margin">Concil. Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinop. <hi>6.</hi> Can. <hi>69.</hi>
               </note> And the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non in the ſixth generall Councell excludeth all lay men from thence, unleſſe it were to come in to offer. And the paſſages in Theodoret between S. Ambroſe and Theodoſius make it manifeſt:<note place="margin">S. Theod. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>18.</hi>
               </note> and they are much miſtaken that produce the Councell of Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople, to prove that communion Tables ſtood in the midſt of the Church.</p>
            <p>But the Service in the Auditory might, and was much of it performed by ſuch as had onely a tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration to read from the Biſhop, without impoſition
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:15184:17"/>of hands by the Presbyterie as Celerinus had from Saint Cyprian.<note place="margin">S. Cypri. <hi>2.</hi> ep. <hi>7.</hi>
               </note> And ſuch had authority to goe into the Pulpit, and read the Service appointed: and when the Reader had finiſhed the Eccleſiaſticall office, then the Expounder or Preacher went up into the Pulpit, and did expound ſome place of Scripture formerly read.<note place="margin">Tert. depraeſer. c. <hi>16.</hi> Euſch. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>34.</hi> S. Cypr. l. <hi>4.</hi> ep. <hi>2.</hi> &amp;. l. <hi>2.</hi> ep. <hi>1.</hi> &amp; l. <hi>1.</hi> ep. <hi>7.</hi> &amp; <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> At this Service were preſent <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chumeni, Competentes, Neophyti,</hi> and all ſorts of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditors, beleevers or unbeleevers. But at the ſecond Service (which began <hi>in Sacrario,</hi> when this firſt Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice ending with a Sermon was done <hi>in Auditorio</hi>) none were admitted to be preſent but only the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. And theſe kneeled behind the Deacons in the midſt of the Presbytery, or Chauncell, and with them ſuch Prieſts as after penance done <hi>ad limina Eccleſiae,</hi> were admitted only <hi>in communionem lai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corum.</hi> For Penitents were permitted to kneele to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the faithfull, but that was <hi>poſt exomolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſin,</hi> as Tertullian thinkes fit to call it, after confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and penance; which was ſo diſtrict and ſevere in thoſe primitive times performed in ſackcloth and aſhes, and the Penitents caſting themſelves downe at the threſholds of the Church doores, and after ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion into the Church, with much adoe granted, then caſting themſelves downe upon their knees be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Altar, or Lords boord, to receive the Prieſts abſolution, that our ſilken eares will be in danger to be galled with the hearing of ſo rough a diſcipline. Yet all of us confeſſe in the Commination, <q>That in the Primitive Church there was ſuch a godly diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, whereby notorious ſinners were put to open penance; and that it is a thing much to be wiſhed for,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:15184:17"/>that ſuch diſcipline were reſtored againe.</q> Biſhop Latimer ſoone miſſed it, or ſome ſuch thing, and complaines of the want thereof; therefore he, with the other godly Biſhops of his time, ſend their wiſhes after it to fetch it againe, till God be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to provide meanes powerfull for the reſtoring thereof.</p>
            <p>Tertullian taxeth the Heretickes of his time for neglect of this decent and godly diſcipline.<note place="margin">Tertul. de praeſer. c. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> They kept no diſtinction of places, nor of Service in their Conventicles. <hi>Quis catechumenus, quis fidelis incer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum eſt; pariter adeunt, pariter audiunt, pariter orant.</hi> The whole heard of them ranne in a rout together, both to Prayers, Sermon, and Sacrament, that you could not know one from another.<note place="margin">Euſeb. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>28</hi> &amp; l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> It was quite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe in the holy Catholike Church. That which Zepherinus required of Natalius, Fabianus of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip, and Saint Cyprian of the Penitents of his time,<note place="margin">S. Cyp. l. <hi>2.</hi> ep. <hi>7</hi>
               </note> make it manifeſt, that there were diſtinction of pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the Church to ranke all ſorts of Chriſtians in. And Saint Ambroſe his practice ſheweth a diſtincti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Service. The Catechumeni being diſmiſſed, <hi>miſſam facere caepi;</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Amb. ep. <hi>33.</hi>
               </note> Saint Ambroſe began not the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Service, as our Church calleth it, at the Altar,<note place="margin">Booke of Faſt <hi>1.</hi> D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m. R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>gi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> before the firſt Service in the body of the Church was finiſhed, and the Catechumeni ſent out: which ſtill is the cuſtome in our Church, and none will ever goe about to put that ſweet harmonie which wee keepe with the Primitive Church out of tune, but ſuch as Tertullian complaines of, Schiſmatickes and Sectaries. And ſo we ſee that all thoſe holy actions which are diſtinctly performed both in the firſt and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:15184:18"/>ſecond ſervice, are all included in this action of brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of bread, <hi>ſicut frangitur in Sacramento corporis Chriſti.</hi> And ſo I come to the ſecond holy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</p>
            <p n="2">2. This is <hi>Preaching.</hi> The Preacher is Saint Paul. What kinde of Sermon then did Saint Paul make? for fit it is that his action be our directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>Saint Pauls preaching is of three kinds: 1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he reaſoned with them, or taught them by way of dialogue. 2 <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, he continued his ſpeech. 3 <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ver. 11. he uſed a long homily, which held from midnight till morning.</p>
            <p>For the firſt: Saint Pauls preaching did not ſtand onely in making a long diſcourſe, which ſome, piti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully periſhing in a dearth of matter, and in an inun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of light and froathie words, trumpet up for the onely preaching: But he gave others leave to ſpeake as well as himſelfe; for that muſt needs be to hold up the dialogue in the text, yet he preached for all that. Wherefore if the Curate catechiſe in the afternoone, as he is commanded, by queſtion and anſwer, which makes the dialogue in the text, this man preacheth. There is therefore no cauſe at all why ſome ſhould take the matter ſo grievouſly, that charge ſhould be given by the King (whom they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver meane to obey therein) that afternoone Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſhould be turned into catechiſing, that is, that one kinde of preaching ſhould be exchanged for an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, the leſſe profitable for the more uſefull. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine alſo it is, that whether they travell all the Scriptures over, and then paſſe on to the ancient
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:15184:18"/>Fathers, they ſhall finde no ground at all for the fruitleſſe and diſobedient exerciſe of their after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noone talent, till they come home to their owne wilfull ſelfe-conceitedneſſe. Our Saviour came not to breake the law, but to fulfill it, who being at Capernaum on a <hi>Sabbath</hi> day preached but once. For <hi>ſtatim è Synagogâ</hi> from the Synagogue he went immediately to Simons houſe to dinner, where Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons wives mother miniſtred unto them, <hi>Mar.</hi> 1.31. and there ſtayed healing diſeaſes till ſunne ſet, and went no more to the Synagogue to preach in the afternoon. The law that enjoined afternoon Sermons for keeping their <hi>Sabbath,</hi> was not then knowne to the Phariſes themſelves, who elſe were apt enough to have laid it in his diſh at ſupper;<note place="margin">Troubles at Franckford, pag. <hi>194.</hi>
               </note> no nor to theſe mens progenitors for 1565. yeares after, as by their owne confeſſion may appeare.</p>
            <p>True it is Saint Peter preached once at the ninth houre, or at three a clocke in the afternoone, <hi>Act.</hi> 3.1. but the occaſion, place, and other circumſtances be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo extraordinary, his example binds us no more to doe the like, than Saint Pauls here doth to preach in an upper chamber all night long.</p>
            <p>The holy Fathers alſo in the beſt times had their Sermons in the forenoons, and it will be hard for the beſt or ſtubborneſt of them all to ſhew a Sermon preached by any of the Fathers in the afternoone, Saint Baſil onely excepted, who had his ſecond and ninth homily in the afternoone;<note place="margin">Socrat l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>21.</hi> Niceph. l. <hi>12.</hi> c. <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> becauſe as Socrates and Nicephorus affirme, the cuſtome in Caeſare a was not to preach in the forenoone, but <hi>Epiſcopi &amp; Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerdotes poſt lucernarum accenſiones ſacras Scripturae
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:15184:19"/>populo exponunt,</hi> the people have the Scripture, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded to them in the afternoone. Their preaching was but expounding (as they call it) and that but once neither. Why then ſhould they not yeeld to change their afternoone diſcourſing into preaching by way of dialogue, as St. Paul here did?</p>
            <p>Secondly, St. Paul preached <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, all the while he was in his Homilie. What his Homilie was, it is hard for me to ſay; whether it was one that himſelfe made, and did not reade; or one that he read, and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other made. An Homilie I am ſure it was, and it may be made by all the Apoſtles, or the chiefe of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, as (Bucer ſaies) our Homilies were penned by ſome eminent Preachers.</p>
            <p>I pray you tell me, (when Saint Paul went through divers Churches, as now he did, to eſtabliſh them in the faith, and to that end took with him <hi>dogmata,</hi> the decrees made by the Apoſtles and Elders that were at Jeruſalem,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act,</hi> 16.4.</note> and delivered them to the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to be kept) whether he did reade them or no, or delivered them as a Roll ſealed up? If he read them, there's his homilie. And moſt certaine it is he read them, even by his owne rule. For if he cauſed Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles from ſome one man to be read in the Church by him that brought them, it is more than evident that himſelfe bringing the Decrees of the Apoſtles and Elders, he would not in any ſort tranſgreſſe his owne rule, but doe the decrees, himſelfe and the Church that right as to reade them, that the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches might ſee what it was that he delivered them to keep, and be fully aſſured that himſelfe walked in the ſelfe ſame ſteps with the reſt of the Apoſtles, and
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:15184:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſo be enabled to ſtop the mouths of all falſe Apoſtles, who objected that againſt him, and thereby be fully eſtabliſhed in the faith, which was the only end of his comming; which could not have beene wrought nor obtained, if theſe Decrees had not beene read at all, or read by any other. Wherefore I take it for a cleare truth, that St. Paul read the Decrees, and ſure I am by the word uſed in the text, that when he read them and did no more but reade them, without adding or diminiſhing, that he preached by way of Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </p>
            <p>Reading of Homilies then is preaching,<note place="margin">Concil. Rhem. Can. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> and ſo adjudged by the learned Biſhops in the Councell of Rhemes. The Canon concerneth Biſhops them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, <hi>Ut Epiſcopi Sermones &amp; Homilias ſanctorum Patrum, prout omnes intelligant, ſecundum proprieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem linguae praedicare ſtudeant.</hi> The Canon ſaies not <hi>praedicari ſtudeant,</hi> but <hi>praedicare;</hi> themſelves muſt give good example, not only in preaching Sermons of their owne making, as it is appointed, Can. 14. (which ſome cry up for the only preaching) but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo read and interpret the Homilies of holy Fathers themſelves, which is alſo here called preaching.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe when the Diptychs, containing the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the foure firſt generall Councels,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Conſtantinop.</hi> 5. <hi>Act.</hi> 10.</note> and of Saint Leo were read, <hi>pro utilitate &amp; pace Eccleſiae praedicantur,</hi> they are ſaid to be preached for the profit and peace of the Church. This reading of Decrees is called preaching in the Councell of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople.</p>
            <p>If then reading of decrees of the Apoſtles, and by that preſident reading of Diptychs and Homilies be
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:15184:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>preaching, and uſed for the profit and peace of the Church, and for the eſtabliſhing of them in the faith, then ſurely is reading of leſſons, Epiſtle and Goſpel, much more preaching, and the Reader is a Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher.</p>
            <p>The Councell of Aquiſgrane layeth downe the office of a Reader,<note place="margin">Concil. Aq. c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> and to prevent all exceptions <hi>ex ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicâ authoritate,</hi> and ſaith thus, <hi>Lectores ſunt qui verbum Dei praedicant,</hi> Readers are Preachers. This they might learne of Saint Ambroſe,<note place="margin">S. Ambr. in eph. c. <hi>4.</hi> v. <hi>11.</hi> S. Cypr. ep. <hi>4.</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi> &amp; ep. <hi>5.</hi> l. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> and he of Saint Cyprian. Saint Cyprian gives onely a toleration to read unto Celerinus nobly deſcended, yet ſayes it will make more for his honour <hi>in coeleſti praedicatione fieri generoſum,</hi> to be made a Gentleman for his hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly preaching; yet this preaching was but rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding. And further ſaith, that there is nothing wherein a Confeſſour <hi>magis proſit,</hi> can more profit his brethren, than by reading the Goſpel, <hi>unde Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres fiunt,</hi> whereby Confeſſours are made Martyrs. This was the doctrine of Origen before him.<note place="margin">Orig. hom. <hi>10.</hi> in Gen.</note> Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding then is preaching, nay heavenly preaching; and there is nothing more profitable for the Church, nor more powerfull to make the moſt perfect men of God of all other, even to make Martyrs.</p>
            <p>What ſhall we thinke then of T. C. and ſuch as he hath ſeduced, that traduce Readers for dumb dogs, blinde guides, empty feeders, and ſay that rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding is ſo farre from making the man of God perfect, that rather the quite contrary may be confirmed? Whether doe you not thinke that this bleſſed Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop and Martyr, and theſe holy and learned Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops would not ſharpely have cenſured the broa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:15184:20"/>of ſuch doctrine within their Dioceſſes? or will you condemne them, their doctrine and Canons, to deifie T.C.?</p>
            <p>For my part, <hi>qui Bavium non odit, amet tua Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina Maevi,</hi> he that deteſteth not the Father of ſuch Schiſmatickes, with their Brood, I wiſh him no worſe but that he may fall ſo farre in love with the pure zeale of thoſe wandring Danites, their refined brethren led by ſuch guides, that they may beleeve their ſpies, and follow them <hi>per mare, per terras,</hi> into new Laiſh, to dwell in a Land of their owne,<note place="margin">Cottons Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon.</note> and to goe no more out, but make themſelves happy with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out corrivalls, under an Ephod and Prieſt of Micha's owne making. And ſurely if they did beleeve their owne doctrines, and would be honeſt and true to their owne poſitions, I cannot ſee how they ſhould ſtay here longer than for a good wind. The govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Church (they ſay) is Babyloniſh: while they ſtay here they are in the midſt of Baby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lon, therefore the rites of Babylon they will not uſe; and there is no reaſon that they ſhould. Why then doth not that loud cry awaken their conſciences that calls them out hence, <hi>Come out of her my people, that you be not partaker in her plagues?</hi> How doe they thinke that any man ſhould truſt them, that are ſo falſe to their owne friends, their own followers, their owne faith and doctrine, and will forſake them all, and with Demas embrace this preſent world in the midſt of Babylon, with ſo great hazzard of the plagues of Babylon?</p>
            <p>Doubtleſſe theſe Church Schiſmatickes are the moſt groſſe, nay the moſt tranſparent Hypocrites,
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:15184:21"/>and moſt void of conſcience of all others. They will take the benefit of the Church, but abjure the doctrine and diſcipline of the Church. Theſe are whoriſh and Babyloniſh: But tythe milke is not whoriſh, if it be not mingled with water; nor a tithe ſheafe Babyloniſh, till it be as big as great Babylon it ſelfe. Is not this ridiculous hypocriſie? If their ſtomackes be ſo queazie to riſe againſt theſe things, becauſe their pure noſtrill reſenteth the dip of the Popes foot in them, let them begin to abandon the Pope in that which he hath by Canons and Bulls al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, <hi>viz.</hi> in tiths and offrings; and not in that which he never allowed, in our Booke of Common Prayer, wherein is ſet downe the onely direction we have for keeping the Lords day in ſuch godly duties as the text ſpecifieth. If their condemnation or want of the Popes confirmation of that holy booke, were of power to hang a mill-ſtone about it, and to caſt it into the bottome of the ſea of their abominations, we might lie downe in ſorrow, and cry our laſt <hi>Icha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bod,</hi> the glorie is departed from Iſrael: And they might with the voice of melody ſing and ſay, With great wreſtlings have I wreſtled with my ſiſter, and have prevailed to make her a very Babylon, and to cauſe her to ſit in the duſt, and never to riſe any more. But praiſed be the Lord, whoſe day we wil ever keep, and not their <hi>Sabbath,</hi> that hath delivered us as a prey out of their teeth.</p>
            <p>I will now conclude this point. We ſee that brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king of bread, and preaching in ſuch ſort as hath beene explained, are the holy exerciſes uſed by St. Paul and his Diſciples, and by the holy Martyrs and
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:15184:21"/>godly Fathers in the Primitive Church for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the Lords day.</p>
            <p>From hence then we may conclude who are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faners of that moſt holy day; not thoſe that uſe harmleſſe recreations, or do ſome ſmall uſefull chare, or perhaps take a nap on the Lords day: But thoſe that do theſe with Eutichus when Paul is preaching, or (as St. Auſtine ſaies) <hi>caeteris ad Eccleſiam pergen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S Aug. Ser. de tem. <hi>251.</hi>
               </note> when others goe to Church, or in ſuch ſort that <hi>publicum impediunt miniſterium</hi> (as Chemnitius ſpeakes) they hinder them from the publicke ſervice of God.<note place="margin">Chem. de Feſt. p. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Thoſe alſo are profaners of the Lords day, (as Origen ſaies) <hi>qui ſacris lectionibus ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ga vertunt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Orig. hom. <hi>11.</hi> in Jer.</note> that make baſe account of Scripture read; and ſuch (as Saint Cyrill ſayes) that will not <hi>Eccleſiaſtico officio intereſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Cyril. in Je, l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> come to Church till Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice be ended, and the Sermon to begin: and ſuch (as St. Auſtine ſayes) that <hi>cogunt Sacerdotem ut abbrevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et miſſam,</hi> make the Prieſt to curtaile divine Service,<note place="margin">S. Aug. Ser. de tem. <hi>251.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>aut ut ad eorum libitum cantet,</hi> or ſing or ſay it after their fancy, not <hi>antiphonatim,</hi> the Prieſt one verſe and the people another; which factious diſpoſition St. Baſil reproves in ſome Clergie men of Neocaeſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea,<note place="margin">S. Baſil. ep. <hi>45<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </note> that being againſt the practice of the univerſall Church continued from Ignatius, who was directed thereunto by an Angell, as Socrates affirmeth. Thoſe yet are worſe profaners of the Lords day,<note place="margin">Socrat. l. <hi>6.</hi> c. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> that will not reade the Letanie on it, for <hi>excitavit Diabolus</hi> (ſaies St. Chryſoſtome in plaine termes) the Divell himſelfe, and no body elſe,<note place="margin">S. Chryſ. Ser. antequam iret in exil. Bed. hiſ. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> hath ſtirred up thoſe that make brabbles <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, about the Letanie to bring it into contempt, which was the meanes of the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:15184:22"/>firſt converſion of our Engliſh Nation.</p>
            <p>Trypho the Jew alledgeth <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.13. to prove Juſtin Martyr a breaker of the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> who tells him that the Prophet I ſay requireth no more than was before commanded by Moſes in the law,<note place="margin">S. Juſt. in Tryph. Tom. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto he had given his anſwer.</p>
            <p>This very place of Scripture our zealous <hi>Sabba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarians</hi> his iſſue, borrow of that Jew, and uſe as a ſword to cut off all ſports and recreations on their <hi>Sabbath,</hi> with all other actions of our owne, becauſe we are forbidden <hi>to doe our owne will, or to ſpeake our owne words, or vaine words on the Sabbath.</hi> But let them beware that with Saul they fall not upon their owne ſword. For I pray you deale clearely, and ſay, whether thoſe that will neither preach, pray, cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſe, adminiſter the Sacraments, nor performe any part of divine Service, as Gods Magiſtrate appoints, doe not their owne wills? His I am ſure they doe not. And when they make new gloſſes and expoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of Scripture, never received in the Church of God, nor delivered by any ancient Father, whom by Canon they are bound to follow, and call the Lords day a <hi>Sabbath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Lib. Can. An. <hi>1571.</hi> Can. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> whether they doe not ſpeake their owne words?</p>
            <p>And when they uſe vaine repetitions, and babling in their prayers and preaching, ſaying, Lord, Lord, oftener in one prayer, than there are words in all the Lords prayer, doe not uſe vaine words, and take the Lords name in vaine; and be not punctually thoſe whom our Saviour reproves by Saint <hi>Marke, cap.</hi> 7. <hi>ver.</hi> 7. <hi>In vanum me colunt,</hi> they honour me with vaine words, vaine gloſſes and expoſitions, vaine
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:15184:22"/>babling and repetitions, crying, Lord, Lord, and all in vaine, for they doe not the thing that I ſay. For I ſay, when you pray ſay <hi>Our Father,</hi> &amp;c. and thus you will not doe, but will pray an houre together before a Sermon: yet though Chriſt and his Church com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand them to ſay it, they will not doe it.</p>
            <p>He that can ſay <hi>Corban,</hi> and cry up the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> the <hi>Sabbath,</hi> it is a ſufficient <hi>Superſedeas,</hi> it is duty and piety enough, though he neither honour Father nor Mother, Chriſt, nor the King his Vicegerent, nor the Church his Spouſe. Let thoſe then that are ſo violent againſt ſuch as recreate themſelves civilly and modeſtly, in ſuch wiſe as Gods Magiſtrate doth allow, to prove them <hi>Sabbath</hi> breakers, which is no ſin at all, look they be not found ſuch as with an high hand and ſtiffe neck profane the Lords day in deſpite of Authority, and ſo adde drunkenneſſe to thirſt, namely, to their open profanation, rebellion or diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, which is as the ſinne of witchcraft. From which leproſie waſhing ſeven times in Jordan will not cleanſe them, unleſſe they can prove Gods Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate <hi>Nebuchodonoſor,</hi> and themſelves the three children.</p>
            <p>Sure I am their diſobedient and ſcornfull contempt of our Church Liturgie is to many godly and lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned men, farre their Superiours in theſe reſpects, ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſcandalous; and may drive many that reverence antiquity with us, and for that cauſe ſtand well affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted to our Church, to withdraw themſelves from us. That it is not to be wondred at if Recuſants ſhould increaſe, but rather it is a wonder that there are no more. For how can any man of judgement
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:15184:23"/>and diſcretion like that Liturgie and forme of divine Service, which our ſelves (they ſay) contemne, ſcorne, mangle, and miſuſe as we liſt, and ſome reject utterly as unlawfull and Antichriſtian? Doe we tell them it is poiſon, and doe they ſee us caſt it out of our hands, and doe we wonder that they will not run and take it up and eat it, or that they refuſe the uſe of it, as we doe, or rather forbeare the Church till it be uſed?</p>
            <p>They will uſe no Croſſe forſooth, nor Surplice, meet no coarſe at the Church gate, Church no wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, read no Service on Wedneſdayes, Fridayes, Saturdayes, Holy dayes, nor on their Eeves, will not ſtand at the Creed, nor Goſpel, kneele at the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion, nor bowe the knee at the bleſſed name of the Lord JESUS, nor goe in proceſſion, or keep their perambulations, nor doe any thing at all as the Church appoints; yet the worſt is, they would be eſteemed members, nay pillars of the Church: whereas indeed they are neither the one nor the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, but a diſeaſe, a fretting canker, a dangerous fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in the Church. They are wandring ſtarres, and diſaſterous planets, who have and doe blaſt the moſt flouriſhing and glorious Church under the cope of Heaven, were it not that theſe withered branches doe appeare her onely ſpots of diſgrace. And becauſe they are ſuch, hence it is that the Church for her owne ſafety is faine to renounce all defence of them and their doctrines againſt the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſts. Therefore ſhe ought not in right to be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braided or deſerted for any thing they ſay or doe.</p>
            <p>The Church knoweth, and every member there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:15184:23"/>of ſeeth, that this generation had eaten out her bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els long ſince, like Vipers, and become her deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but that by Gods providence they have as ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently diſcovered their malicious projects to be bent alike for the caſting downe of Crownes and Scepters, and lawes of the Land, and the Profeſſours thereof, as for the trampling under their feet of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and corner'd Caps, Biſhops and ſuch as exerciſe juriſdiction under them, together with our Booke of Common Prayer, and Canons Eccleſiaſticall. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Church hath little cauſe to honour them as her children, with her defence, before they will be brought to honour her and her orders, nay to ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the Lord and his day, in breaking of bread, and preaching in ſuch ſort as ſhee hath learned of St. Paul, and delivered in the Booke of Common Prayer. And now I have done with them.</p>
            <p>The laſt point, with which I will conclude, is the place where Saint Paul preached: <hi>In an upper cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let no man thinke from hence, that he hath got a warrant to doe ſo in theſe dayes. This is the third time Paul came to Troas. At the firſt time, being 41. yeares of age (as ſome account) he was called a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way by a viſion into Macedonia, and made no ſtay at all.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 16.</note> About three yeares after he came thither again to looke for Titus,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> but not finding him, he onely fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted the brethren, and went away in great heavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. Now in the 47<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. yeare of his age he comes hither againe, and ſtayes but ſeven dayes; ſo that he had no time to take order for building of a Church to preach, and to celebrate the Euchriſt in.
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:15184:24"/>Follow him therefore to Corinth, where he ſtayd a yeare and ſixe moneths, where we ſhall not take him preaching in an upper chamber.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Acts</hi> 18.11.</note> For ſo ſoone as the Jewes had driven him out of the Synagogue, and beaten Soſthenes the Ruler of the Synagogue for ſuffering him to preach on the <hi>Sabbath</hi> day, and alſo blaſphemed his doctrine in all probability tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the obſervation of the Lords day, ſaying, as it was maliciouſly reported amongſt the Jewes, that the Lord was not riſen, but that his Diſciples ſtole him away, therefore the day of his reſurrection ought not to be kept, nor preached on their <hi>Sab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath,</hi> tending ſo much to the overthrow thereof. Upon this or the like blaſphemy St. Paul tooke juſt occaſion to renounce them and their Synagogue, ſaying, <hi>From henceforth I goe unto the Gentiles.</hi> And ſo immediately he tooke order for a publike place to meet in, ſo large, that men and women, learned and unlearned, beleevers and unbeleevers might all meet together. And this place was a CHURCH.</p>
            <p>If the whole Church be come together into one Place, they may ſpeake languages, provided that they doe interpret, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33. Yea, but how doth it appeare that this one place is a Church? Why be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe himſelfe calls it ſo, ſaying, <hi>In the church I had rather ſpeake five words, &amp;c. ver.</hi> 19. So their com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming together to eat the Lords body was into one place, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11.20. and this one place was a Church, <hi>ver.</hi> 18. <hi>When yee come together in the Church, I heare, &amp;c. this is not to eat the Lords body.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Church, or publike place of meeting is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wayes diſtinguiſhed from private houſes. The
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:15184:24"/>Church was free for all to come into, Jewes or Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, beleevers or unbeleevers, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.24. ſo were not private houſes. In private houſes women might ſpeake: not ſo in the Church. In private houſes men might be covered, and women uncovered:<note place="margin">S. Chryſ. in Act. ho. <hi>21.</hi> &amp; de Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer dot. l. <hi>6.</hi> &amp; hom. de eucha, in encaeniis.</note> not ſo in the Church. In the Church reverence was to be given to the Angels which attend the Lord our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour at his table <hi>in tremendis myſteriis</hi> (as St. Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome ſpeakes) where he is truely and really pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: not ſo in private houſes. In private houſes they might eate and drinke: not ſo in the Church. Theſe Churches had Biſhops ſet over them, which had power of excommunication, penance, and abſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; which was not uſed in private houſes, but onely in the Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7. To theſe Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches belonged ſtockes of money, whereby Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes and others were maintained at the diſcretion of the Biſhop, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.9. which authority they had not in private houſes: but were at the curteſie of the owners to be received or not.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 10.10.</note> In theſe Churches ſtood the Lords boord, which was not placed in any private houſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.21. This table of the Lord is called alſo an Altar, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.13. <hi>They that waite of the Altar are partakers of the Altar;</hi> which is not to be underſtood of Iſrael after the fleſh. For <hi>ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bemus Altare,</hi> we under the Goſpel have an Altar, <hi>Heb.</hi> 15.10. And ſo is the word Altar, and Lords ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble indifferently and alike anciently uſed in the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings of the Fathers, who beſt knew how to expound Scripture. Theſe were ſome Tables or Altars of ſtone, <hi>quia Chriſtus eſt lapis angularis:</hi> ſome were of wood, the better to expreſſe his death on the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:15184:25"/>tree,<note place="margin">S. Juſt. in Tryph. Tom. <hi>2.</hi> Tert. l. <hi>4.</hi> adv. Marcion.</note> 
               <hi>poſuerunt lignum in panem ejus, Jer.</hi> 11. Theſe woodden Altars or Tables the furious Circumcelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons brake downe in St. Auguſtines time.</p>
            <p>So that from the 47<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. yeare of Saint Pauls age, which was the 57<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of our Sauiour, we may count out of Scripture, that the devotion of Gods people began in building of Churches for breaking of bread and preaching, and with them began the ſolemne ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of the juriſdiction of Biſhops in excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, penance, confeſsion, and abſolution, which with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Churches could not well be exerciſed. But in Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſticall writers we find the beginning more early, and ſo the uſe continued without interruption in the midſt of all their perſecutions for 287. yeares toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, untill Diocleſians time.</p>
            <p>I might be infinite in this kinde, but I will give you but a touch thereof.<note place="margin">Euſeb. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> The Apoſtles and diſciples ſtaid in Jeruſalem after Chriſts reſurrection twelve yeares together, and preached to the Jewes in their Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues: but becauſe they kept the <hi>Sabbath</hi> no bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter than their Lord did, but began to keepe the Lords day, which the Jewes deteſted, and to neglect the <hi>Sabbath,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Juſtin. de ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit. l. <hi>2.</hi> in Try.</note> which they onely doted on as neceſſary to ſalvation, they are driven out of Jeruſalem, and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſed into ſundry Nations. And in the firſt yeare of their diſperſion, which was about the 47<hi rend="sup">th</hi>. of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour, they began to build Churches to preach and adminiſter the Sacraments in on the Lords day.</p>
            <p>About this time or before a goodly room in The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ophilus his houſe in Antioch,<note place="margin">An Chriſti <hi>38.</hi> Hieron. in ep. <hi>2.</hi> ad Gal. &amp; Euſeb. in Chr. S. Clemen. re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cogd. l. <hi>10.</hi>
               </note> where ten thouſand met at one time, was conſecrated for a Church by St. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and there was placed St. Peters chaire, which
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:15184:25"/>for a long time after there continued.</p>
            <p>S. Mark alſo about the ſame time cauſed divers Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches to be built about Alexandria,<note place="margin">Euſeb. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>16.</hi>
               </note> wherin it was unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to eat and drinke; but they were uſed onely for rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, preaching, and meditating on Gods word, praying, ſinging of Pſalmes, and the like. In the yeare 57. S. Paul cauſed a Church to be built in Corinth, and in divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places. <hi>Anno</hi> 63. Joſeph of Arimathea cauſed a Church to be built in Glaſtonbury.<note place="margin">Hiſt. Eccleſ. Angl.</note> 
               <hi>Erat haec Eccleſia ab ipſis Apoſtolis Domini aedificata,</hi> witneſſeth Henry the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond in his Letters Patents: For being burnt in his time, he takes a Princely care for the building of it againe, as the Kings Majeſtie now doth for the repairing of that goodly edifice of S. Pauls Church, now fallen to decay. <hi>Anno</hi> 71. Creſcens ſent into Galatia by St. Paul,<note place="margin">Euſeb. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>4</hi> Ado.</note> would not content himſelfe to preach in private houſes, but by S. Pauls example cauſed a Church to be built at Vienna. <hi>Anno</hi> 79. St.<note place="margin">Euſeb. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> John cauſed a goodly Church to be built about Epheſus, where himſelf, with an Archbiſhop &amp; di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Biſhops of ſeverall Churches in Aſia, met at a Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>node. This Church ſtood over againſt the hill where he robbed whom S. John converted.<note place="margin">Euſeb. l. <hi>2.</hi> c. <hi>25</hi>
               </note> Gaius Biſhop of Rome affirmeth, that til his time for 220. years together Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches had continued neere unto the Vaticane, built by the Apoſtles, which had Church-yards belonging to them, and where were to be ſeen the Tombs and Monuments of the Apoſtles. <hi>Anno</hi> 110. Ignatius reproved Trajan in a Church. <hi>Anno</hi> 117.<note place="margin">Niceph. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>19</hi> Dion. in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drian.</note> Adrian cauſed Churches to be built for Chriſtians, wherein he forbade any of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane gods to be placed. <hi>Anno</hi> 160.<note place="margin">Euſeb. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>25.</hi>
               </note> Polycarpus received the Sacrament publikely in the Church of Rome. <hi>Anno</hi> 197.<note place="margin">Bed. l. <hi>1.</hi> c. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Lucius King of Great Britaine deſired of Eleuthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:15184:26"/>
               <hi>ut per ejus mandatum fieret Chriſtianus,</hi> which being granted,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lores hiſt.</note> he dedicated the Temples of the Heathen gods to the worſhip of the true God, and made Churches of them, and placed in them 28. Biſhops, and three Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops Seas.<note place="margin">Tertul. adv. Va<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en. &amp; in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>polog.</note> 
               <hi>Anno</hi> 203. Tertullian maketh mention of theſe Churches built before his time, and ſaith that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly they were built upon an hill, (as Iſaac was offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and Chriſt crucified on an hill) and looked towards the Eaſt, <hi>Noſtrae columbae Domus in editis &amp; apertis, &amp; Orientem amat.</hi> Hence it is (ſaith he) that the Heathen traduce us for worſhipping the Sun, <hi>quòd innotuerit nos ad Orientis regionem praecari,</hi> becauſe it is openly known that all we Chriſtians pray unto God in our Churches with our faces to the Eaſt: and if they ſtand not ſo, they are not like Chriſtian Churches, nor judged to be conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated by Chriſtian Biſhops.<note place="margin">S. Ire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Anno</hi> 180. Irenaeus ſaw Poly carpus ſit in his Biſhops chaire in Smyrna. S. James his chaire ſtood in the Church of Jeruſalem for 326. yeares together, ſaith Euſebius, and was there to be ſeen in St. Auſtins time,<note place="margin">Euſeb. l. <hi>5.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi> &amp; l <hi>7.</hi> c. <hi>19.</hi>
               </note> notwithſtanding Diocleſians Decree. <hi>Anno</hi> 239.<note place="margin">S. Aug. l <hi>2.</hi> Con. lit. P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ttl. c. <hi>51.</hi> Cuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>b. l. <hi>6.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>34.</hi>
               </note> Fabianus ſuffered not Philip the firſt Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Emperour to joyn with the faithfull in the Church, before he had ſtood <hi>in loco poenitentium.</hi> And ſo you ſee the zeale of Chriſtians in building of Churches began in the Apoſtles times, and continued for 280. yeares toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at leaſt.</p>
            <p>And how neceſſary it was for the Apoſtles and their ſucceſſours, planters of the Goſpel, to build Churches, and not to pray, preach, adminiſter the Sacraments, or exerciſe Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline of excommunication and abſolution in private houſes,<note place="margin">S. Aug contr. M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. epiſ. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <hi>4</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>m. <hi>6.</hi>
               </note> Irenaeus, Tertullian, St. Auguſtine, and divers godly Fathers tell us. For hereby
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:15184:26"/>Catholickes and good Chriſtians were knowne from Heretickes. For <hi>nullus Haereticorum baſilicam ſuam au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det oſtendere,</hi> Heretickes had no Churches to ſhew, nor chaire wherein they ſucceeded the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Thus Irenaeus confoundeth Valentinus,<note place="margin">S. Iren. l. <hi>3.</hi> c. <hi>3.4.5.</hi>
               </note> Cerdon, and Marcion; they could not ſhew how they ſucceeded the Apoſtles: but he could prove his owne ſucceſsion, and reckon up all thoſe that ſucceeded the Apoſtles in their ſeverall Churches; and ſo ſheweth who ſucceeded Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Paul in the Church of Rome. Whereby their vanity may in part appeare, that againſt all Antiquity, upon idle gheſſes, make fooles beleeve that St. Peter was never at Rome, making the ſucceſsion of Biſhops and truth of the Latine Churches as queſtionable as the Centuriſts orders.</p>
            <p>Thus Tertullian putteth Valentinus and Apelles to it to ſhew their deſcent.<note place="margin">Tertul. de pra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. ſer. c. <hi>11.</hi>
               </note> If they will not be accounted Heretickes, <hi>aedant origines Eccleſiarum ſuarum, evolvant ordinem Sacerdotum, &amp;c. it a ut primus ſit aliquis ex A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolis,</hi> let them ſhew when their Church began, ſo that the firſt founder be an Apoſtle: as Polycarpus was placed by St. John in Smyrna, and Clemens by St. Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the Church of Rome. <hi>Confingant tale quid &amp; Hae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retici,</hi> let Heretickes lay their heads together,<note place="margin">Tert. de prae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſer c. <hi>17.</hi>
               </note> and produce ſuch a pedigree of their faith. Which he was ſure they could not doe: for <hi>ſine matre, ſine ſede extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res vagantur, &amp; Eccleſias non habent.</hi> They were not Chriſtians that had no Churches for 200. yeares after Chriſt: but it plainely appeares by St. Irenaeus and Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian, that they were Hereticks that were ſo long with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Churches. Theſe had no Church for their Mother, no Sea for their Biſhops, nor ſucceſsion of them from
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:15184:27"/>the Apoſtles, but were meere ſtragglers. And for this cauſe (ſaies St. Cyprian) <hi>Haereticus ſanctificare non poteſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">S. Cyp. l. <hi>1.</hi> ep. <hi>12.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quia nec Eccleſiam nec Altarehabet;</hi> an Hereticke can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conſecrate the Sacrament, becauſe he hath neither Church nor Altar; for <hi>Euchariſtia in Altari ſanctifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur.</hi> Without Churches no Sacrament could be conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crated, nor received.</p>
            <p>In this ſort St. Auguſtine confoundeth the Donatiſts and Sectaries of his time;<note place="margin">S. Aug l. <hi>2.</hi> cont. Petil. c. <hi>51.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Numerate Sacerdotes, vel ab ipſa ſede Petri, &amp; in illo ordine, quis cui ſucceſsit videte;</hi> Reckon up your Prieſts, who ſucceeded one another af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter St. Peter in his chaire, if you will be eſteemed mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church. Hereby we may by Gods mercy make good the truth of our Church. For we are able lineally to ſet down the ſucceſsion of our Biſhops from St. Peter to S. Gregorie, and from him to our firſt Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop St. Auſtin, our Engliſh Apoſtle as Biſhop God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>win calls him, downeward to his Grace that now ſits in his chaire, Primate of all England, and Metropoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane.</p>
            <p>This ſucceſsion of Biſhops to the Apoſtles, and exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of Eccleſiaſticall diſcipline, preaching of the word of God, and conſecrating of the Euchariſt on the Lords Boord, or holy Altar, was judged a thing ſo neceſſary by the Apoſtles and their ſucceſſors,<note place="margin">Euſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. l. <hi>8.</hi> c. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> that (as Euſebius reports) Chriſtians never ceaſed building, repairing, and inlarging of Churches, even in the hotteſt times of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecution. And though the Paſtours were many times driven out of them, and wandred up and down in Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines, and Dens, and Caves of the earth, yet they found ſuch favour with the Emperours, that the Churches ſtill continued. And their chaires were never empty, nor the
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:15184:27"/>ſucceſsion of their Biſhops interrupted, no not in Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſians time, when ſo many Churches were demoliſhed.</p>
            <p>True it is Cecilius in Minutius Foelix, and Celſus in Origen, and other Gentiles reviled Chriſtians, and called them Atheiſts, <hi>quia nec templa nec deos haberent,</hi> becauſe they had neither temples nor Gods. And indeed they had no ſuch temples, nor worſhipped ſuch gods as they did. Yet Chriſtians were never without Churches to ſerve the true God in. Howbeit, they were not called Temples, or <hi>Baſilicae,</hi> before the Emperour Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines time, who built them in that ſtately and magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent maner, that they might equalize or ſurmount the ſumptuous Temples erected by the Heathen to Diana, Venus, Jupiter, or other heathen gods.</p>
            <p>Thus neceſsity of Gods ſervice, and exerciſe of Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall diſcipline, cauſed and continued the uſe of Churches from time to time, and their zeale inflamed them to beautifie and adorne them in the moſt ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous maner that might be, that with David and Solomon they might ſhew (ſo farre as their poverty would ſuffer them) in ſuch glorious and magnificent buildings, and by the ſumptuous coſtlineſſe beſtowed in adorning of them with gold, ſilver, and precious ſtones, the incomparable glory, and infinite greatneſſe of the Majeſtie of their God, to whom that poore houſe was dedicated, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whom they preſented themſelves to performe ſuch ſervice as himſelfe and his Vicegerents have appointed: which doubtleſs (as by the practice of S. Paul and the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and the beſt Saints of God, may appeare) is much more acceptable unto him, being performed in an houſe of his own, than if it had been continued in one of ours, in ſome upper chamber, as now upon neceſsity it was.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:15184:28"/>
Wherefore ſince by Gods mercy we doe in part en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the piety and bounty of our Predeceſſours, and have the houſes of God left us to ſerve God in; let us aban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don the irregular faſhion of ſtraggling Schiſmatickes, in making Conventicles, praying, preaching, and breaking bread in corners, private houſes, and dining rooms. And on the other ſide, let us conforme our ſelves in fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quenting the Lords houſe, to the practice of the Lords Church, eſpecially on the Lords day, and ſay with Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, <hi>O come let us goe into the houſe of the Lord, and fall flat on our faces before his footſtoole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if we doe not onely bend or bowe our body to his bleſſed Boord, or holy Altar, but fall flat on our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces before his footſtoole ſo ſoone as ever we approach in ſight thereof, what Patriarch, Apoſtle, bleſſed Martyr, holy or learned Father, would condemne us for it? or rather would not be delighted to ſee their Lord ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured, and their devotion ſo reverently imitated, and ſo good hope given to have it in ſuch ſort continued in the Lords houſe, on the Lords day, by the Lords ſervants, unto the Lords comming againe, who doubtleſſe will then ratifie what he hath already pronounced, <hi>Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are thoſe ſervants whom the Lord when he commeth ſhall finde ſo doing? Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div xml:lang="lat" type="imprimatur">
            <p>PErlegi hanc concionem habitam in viſitatione Trionnali Reverendi in Chriſto Patris Epiſcopi Lincolnienſis, in quâ nihil reperio ſanae doctri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nae aut bonis moribus contrarium, quominùs cum utilitate pablicâ imprima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur; it a tamen ut ſi non intra tres menſes proximè ſequentes typis mandetur, haec licentia ſit omnino irrita.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Ex Aedibus Lambethanis <date>II. Calend. Martii, <hi>1635.</hi>
                  </date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>GUIL. BRAY Rm<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. Patri D. Arch. Cant. Sacellanus domeſticus.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:15184:28"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
